OK, let's get started. Welcome to the 12th
lecture of 6 .006.
This is our second lecture talking about weighted graphs,
and in particular, weighted shortest paths algorithms.
Last time, we talked about weighted graphs. This is a kind of a generalization
of what we mean by distance in an unweighted graph. Instead of each
edge
having a weight of 1, essentially,
we generalize
that to be any integer.
And last time,
we showed how to solve single source shortest paths in a graph
that doesn't have cycles, even if it has 0 or negative weights
in linear time, using
an algorithm called DAG relaxation.
We also showed in that lecture how in linear
time, if we are given the shortest path weights
to all the things reachable in finite dis - or with shortest path distance
that's finite, we can construct a shortest paths tree from those weights
in linear time.
OK, so this is motivating why we're not
really going to talk about parent pointers
for the next couple of lectures. We're just going
to concentrate on these shortest path weights.
And so today, we're
going to be talking about
our most general algorithm we'll be showing
for solving single source shortest paths,
in particular, in graphs
that could contain cycles
and could have negative weights.
So just to recap,
our little roadmap here,
single source shortest paths in linear time. Last time, we
discussed another linear time algorithm, DAG relaxation.
And today, we're going to be talking about Bellman -Ford, which isn't limited
to acyclic graphs. In particular, there could be negative weight cycles
in our graph.
If it has
cycles and has negative weights,
the worry is that we could
have negative weight cycles, in which case,
if a negative
weight cycle is reachable from our source,
then the vertices in that cycle and anything
reachable from that cycle will potentially
have an unbounded number of edges you need to go through.
There's not a bound on the number of edges for a shortest path,
because I could just keep going around that cycle as many times as I want
and get a shorter path, right? And so we assign those distances to be minus
infinity,
OK? So that's what we're going to do today in Bellman
-Ford. In particular, what we're going to do is compute
our shortest path distances, these shortest
path weights,
for every vertex in our graph,
setting the ones that are not reachable to infinity and the ones that are
reachable through a negative weight cycle to minus infinity. And all other
ones, we're
going to set to a finite weight.
And
another thing that we might want is, if
there's a negative weight cycle in the graph,
let's return one, OK? So those are the two
kinds of things that we're trying to solve
in today's lecture,
OK? But before we do that, let's
warm up with two short exercises.
The first one,
exercise one,
OK?
Given an undirected graph,
given undirected graph, f g,
return
whether g contains a negative weight cycle.
Anyone have an idea of how
we can solve this in linear time, actually?
In fact, we
can do it in order e?
No, yes,
yes, reachable from s.
I guess,
let's just say a negative weight
cycle at all,
not in the context
of single source shortest paths.
To detect whether there's a negative weight
n. JASON KUOCHIKA - Ah,
your colleague has determined an
interesting fact about undirected graphs.
If I have a negative weight edge in an undirected
graph, I can just move back and forth along that edge.
That's a cycle of length 2, or I guess, 3 vertices back to where we came
from, that is of negative weight, because I'm just traversing that weight
over and over and over again.
So the question of single source
shortest paths of finding negative weights
is not particularly
interesting in the undirected case.
So if I have every negative weight edge, undirected
edge in my graph, I can just find the reachability from
the vertices,
the endpoints of that edge,
and label them as minus delt. Basically, if
the connected component containing s
has a negative weight edge,
then everything in the graph is accessible from a negative weight cycle.
So this is not such an interesting problem. And so we're going to restrict
our discussion today to
directed graphs.
So this is if and only if exists
negative weight edge.
OK,
exercise 2,
kind of a little preview for what's to come. We're actually not going to
show you an algorithm directly that meets this Bellman -Ford running time, v
times e.
What instead we're going to show you is an
algorithm that solves single source shortest paths.
Single source
shortest paths in order,
v times v plus e time.
OK, what is that? That's v squared plus v times
e, right? That's close to what this v times e is.
OK, that's what we're
going to show you.
But if I had such an algorithm,
can anyone tell me a single source shortest
paths algor -
how we can use this algorithm to solve single
source shortest paths in v, just v times e time?
Show how to solve SSSP in order,
v times e.
I guess we can put a dot there as
well.
OK,
so this is a little tricky.
It's kind of related to the difference we had between the reachability
problem and the single source shortest paths problem that we saw last lecture,
right?
When are these asymptotically different in their
upper bound is when v is asymptotically larger than e,
right?
But the connected
component containing S
can have at
most e vertices,
or order e.
It can actually have at
most e plus 1 vertices
because otherwise it wouldn't be connected.
OK,
so
what we can do if we had such an algorithm,
we could first,
when we're given our graph, explore everything in the graph
using BFS or DFS, find all the things reachable from S,
and then
just throw away everything else.
Now I have a graph for
which v is
asymptotically no bigger than e.
And then we can use this algorithm to solve single source shortest paths
in v times e time. OK, I'm not going to write all that down here. You can
see it in the notes.
Yeah?
Does this work if your graph isn't simple?
Does this work if your graph isn't simple? I haven't thought about
it. We are not going to talk about non -simple graphs in this class,
but probably not
because you've got a lot of edges.
Though in our class, if we're
talking about single source shortest paths,
if we have multiple edges
between two vertices,
we can just take the minimum weight one because
it's never better to take the larger ones.
Does that answer
your question? Great.
All right, so those are our warm
-ups.
That's our goal.
We need to find an algorithm for single
source shortest paths in general graphs,
potentially graphs
with cycles, and negative weights,
and solve it in this v times linear kind of
time.
Does that make sense?
All right,
so first,
before we get to the algorithm,
we're going to discuss a
little bit about shortest paths in general.
If we didn't have, the problem here
is negative weights. How do we find,
if we had negative weight cycles, there seems to be these
problems because we could have minus infinities in our deltas.
But if we didn't
have negative weights,
I'd like to assert to you that our shortest
paths, even if they are negative weights,
are going to be simple.
They won't repeat vertices.
So that's the first thing
we're going to show you.
Let's see.
Simple shortest paths.
So claim.
I'm going to give my claims numbers today
just because I'm going to have a lot of them.
If
my shortest path distance
from s to some vertex is finite,
meaning it's not
infinite or minus infinite,
some finite value,
there exists
a shortest path,
a shortest s to v path
that
is simple.
And remember, simple means
not going through a vertex more than once.
All right,
how are we going to prove this?
Consider
if this claim was not true, right?
If
every shortest path
contains a cycle, essentially, right?
It repeated a vertex.
Then
my path looks something
like this.
I mean,
there's some vertices along here,
and then I go to v.
So here's s, and then there's some cycle. I repeat
some vertex. I'm going to call this cycle c.
OK?
Now,
what do I know about this path? I know that
it's a shortest path,
and it has finite weight,
right?
So in particular,
this path, this
delta distance, is not minus infinity. But
if this is not minus infinity, what
do I know about the weight of this cycle?
It's not negative. Yeah, it can't be negative, right? Because
if it was negative, I could keep going around this cycle,
and this
would have a non -finite weight,
shortest path distance from s,
right? So I know this is,
you know, can't be negative, so it must be 0 or positive,
right? But if it's 0 or positive, and this is a shortest path,
right, went through this cycle,
then I could remove it.
And now I have
a new path with one fewer cycle.
I could just keep doing this
to create a simple path.
OK?
So that checks out.
OK.
So
that's interesting. If
it's simple,
what do we know about
the number of edges in a
simple shortest path? How many could there
possibly be? How long in number of edges
could a simple shortest path be? If I can't
repeat vertices,
right, I can have at most v vertices on my simple path, which
means I can use at most v minus 1 edges, right, fence posting,
right?
So simple paths
have
at most v minus 1 edges.
That's
a nice little thing I'd
like to box off.
That's a really
nice property, right?
So
while a shortest path here could
have an infinite number of edges,
right,
if the shortest path distance is finite, I
know I only have to check paths
that use up
to v minus 1 edges. In
particular, this
is finitely bounded in terms of the number of paths
I have to consider. It's exponential, potentially,
right? But at least it's finite.
OK?
I potentially had to check
every possible path
of which there could be
infinite if there's cycles in my graph. OK.
So I
have an idea.
OK? What
if I could
find shortest path distances by
limiting the number of edges I go through,
right?
So not the full shortest
path, distance from s to v,
but
let's limit the number of edges I'm allowed to go through. And let's talk
about those shortest path distances just among the paths that have at most
a certain number of edges.
I'm going to call
this k edge distance.
And I'm just going
to provide a little notation here.
Instead of having a delta, I'll have a delta k
here. That means how many edges I'm limited by.
OK? So from s
to v is
shortest
s to v path using, at most,
k edges.
Short weight.
Weight
of
a shortest path,
shortest s to
v path using, at most,
k edges.
OK? And these notions seem somewhat
symmetric, right? If I were able to compute
this thing for v minus 1,
right,
for
all the vertices,
then if the distance is finite,
then I'll have
successfully computed
the real shortest paths because of this statement,
right? Now, that doesn't mean that if this is
the shortest path, it doesn't mean the
other way, right? If this is minus infinity,
right, if the shortest
path distance is minus infinity,
it doesn't
say anything about what this is,
right? It just says the shortest
path using, at most, v minus 1 vertices,
using, at most,
v minus 1 edges would
be whatever this is.
But really, the shortest path length needs
to consider an infinite number of edges,
right? So it doesn't really tell us much.
It doesn't really tell us much about that.
But for the finite ones, it does. It works
well.
And so if we are able to compute this thing
for k equals v minus 1 in
a graph that doesn't contain
negative weight cycles, we'd be done,
right?
I
claim to you a stronger statement
that if
the shortest path using,
at most, v edges
from s to v
is less than, strictly less than,
delta of v minus 1,
right? This is all in
the subscript here, right?
Basically, this is the
shortest path distance
of any simple path,
right? And possibly one that also contains cycles. But
definitely, it includes all the simple paths, right?
If there's a shorter path
to my vertex
that goes through more than
v minus 1 edges, this path can't be simple,
right?
Because it goes through a vertex more than once.
Otherwise, it would be included in this distance set,
right? So if this is the case,
and I found a shorter path to v that uses v edges,
yeah, that uses v edges, that path can't be simple,
which means that path,
or some path there,
contains a negative weight cycle,
OK?
So if this is true, then I know
that
the real
shortest path distance from s to v
must be minus infinity.
Right?
I'm going
to call such a vertex a witness,
right? If we can find a vertex that has this property, I
mean, I haven't shown you how to compute these things yet,
right? But if I were able to find a vertex
v,
and these are capital Vs,
if you're having trouble,
this v is different than
this v. This is cardinality, right?
If we can find such a vertex v,
that certifies that there
is a negative weight cycle in our graph.
So I'm going
to call v is a witness,
OK?
So if
this property is true, it's a witness, and it
definitely has this. Is it possible, you think,
I'm going to claim to
you that it's possible
that a
vertex could have minus infinite distance,
but not have this property hold,
OK?
I
could probably give you an example. I don't have one
off the top of my head right now, but that's possible.
You could imagine there might be no path
going to a vertex on a negative weight cycle
that goes
through exactly v edges,
right? It
might go through more edges, a shorter one,
right?
So
this
equation would be, it would be an equality and
would not certify that this is true, right?
But I claim to you,
if a vertex has this property, if
its shortest
path distance is minus infinite,
then it must be reachable from a
witness, OK? So that's the claim.
If
delta sv is minus infinity,
then v is reachable
from
a witness,
reachable from a vertex
that has this property, that has
this property.
And if it's reachable from something that
has minus infinity shortest path weight,
then I can take that path,
go to my reachable vertex, and that's all I'm going
to do. It's also a minus infinite path, right?
OK, so how do we prove this?
Well, let's consider,
I'm going to
state a somewhat stronger
statement
that we'll prove instead,
OK? It suffices to prove that every
negative weight cycle contains a witness.
If we were to prove that,
right,
then
every vertex with this property,
every vertex
with this property has,
is
reachable
from a negative weight cycle by definition,
OK?
So every,
prove
every
negative
weight
cycle contains witness,
right? If we can prove that every negative
weight cycle contains a witness,
then
every vertex reachable from one of those witnesses,
in particular reachable from a negative weight cycle,
has, is,
has shortest path distance minus infinity,
and that should prove the claim, right? Is,
this thing has to
be reachable from a negative weight cycle.
If all of these negative
weight cycles contain witnesses,
then all of these vertices
are reachable from a witness. OK, great,
great.
Confusing myself there
for a second.
OK,
so let's
consider a negative weight cycle
in G, OK? This is
a directed negative weight cycle,
recall,
OK? This would be
my negative
weight cycle C, right?
So I'm going to say that
the vertices in this thing, the weights,
has negative weight.
And I'm going
to have a little bit of notation. If I have
a vertex V here,
I'm going to say that its predecessor in the
cycle, I'm just going to call it V prime,
OK? That's just some notation.
Shortest
path distances to every vertex in my graph,
shortest path distance going through at most V vertices, and the
shortest path distance going through at most V minus 1 vertices,
then
I know the following thing holds.
Delta
V going from S to V for
any vertex in my cycle
can't be bigger than delta V minus
from S
to U.
Plus the weight,
sorry, not U, V prime,
its predecessor,
plus the weight
going
from the predecessor to my vertex.
Why is that?
Because this is the weight of some vertex.
This
is the shortest path distance
to my predecessor
using one fewer edge.
And so this,
in particular, is the weight of some path.
That uses V edges.
So
if this is the shortest such path distance,
this has to
upper bound it, right?
At least,
at most, yeah. Is
that the triangle inequality? That is a
statement of the triangle inequality. Thank you.
All right,
so yes, this is just by triangle
inequality.
OK,
now what we can say is let's take this
equation, summed over all vertices, in my cycle.
So I'm just going to add
summation here of all vertices in my cycle
of this whole thing.
I'm going to
do that out a little bit neater.
Summation
of delta, not D, delta
V S V,
I
guess I don't need
this open parentheses,
equals,
or less than or equal to, sum of V in C of
delta V minus 1 V prime.
OK,
and here, I'm summing
over V in C.
And this is just my notation
for it's the predecessor, right?
And then
I'm going to sum over the weights
in my cycle,
V in C, right? These are
the sum of the weights in my cycle.
Well,
what do I know about this cycle?
This is just
the weight of C, right?
Weight of C.
That's awful handwriting.
C, what
do I know about the
weight of the cycle? It's negative, right?
So
this is less
than 0, which means that if I remove this,
this needs to
be a strict equality,
right?
But if this,
if the sum of all of these is less,
strictly less than the sum of all these,
we can't have none of the vertices in my graph
satisfying, not satisfying this property,
right?
Right?
If all of them
are not witnesses,
then this thing
is bigger than this thing, at least as big as this thing,
for every vertex in my cycle, which is a contradiction,
right?
So the claim holds, if
we have
a negative infinite shortest path distance,
then V is reachable from a witness. So it
suffices for us to find all the witnesses,
find all
the vertices reachable from the witnesses,
and then mark them as minus infinity. Does
that make sense?
OK.
So
now we finally are able
to get to our algorithm.
All right.
Bellman -Ford.
And
what I'm going to show you today is a little different
than what is normally presented as Bellman -Ford.
The original
Bellman -Ford algorithm
does something a
little different.
And because it does something a little
different, which we'll talk about at the end,
it's a little hairier to analyze. I'm going
to
show you a modification that is a little easier to analyze and has
this nice property that we're going to be able to use the algorithm
to give us a negative
weight cycle if it exists. OK?
So
we're going to
say this is maybe a modified Bellman -Ford.
And the idea here is to
make a vertex
associated, make many versions of a vertex.
OK? And I want this version of the vertex to
correspond to whether I came here using 0,
0 edges, 1 edge,
2 edges,
3 edges. I have a different version of the
vertex for each one of these,
for a path going through,
at most, a certain number of edges.
OK. So this is an idea
called graph duplication.
Idea.
Graph duplication.
And this is a common technique for solving
graph -related problems
because essentially what
I get to do is I get to store information.
Right? If
I'm having different versions of a vertex,
I can have that vertex
correspond to
reaching that vertex in a different state.
OK?
So that's what we're going to do
here.
The idea here
is make
v
plus 1 levels,
basically
duplicate vertices in our graph,
where vertex vk in level
k represents reaching
vertex
v using, at most,
k edges.
OK. So this definition
seems
similar to what we're doing up here. Right?
If we have
vertices that have this property,
then their
shortest paths in this new graph
might correspond to these k edge distances. And really, the name of
the game here is to compute these two for every vertex because then if
delta is finite,
then this guy will be the length of our
shortest path. And if they're different,
that'll be a witness and
we can explore from it.
OK?
So
we connect edges
from one level
to only
higher levels,
basically levels with
a higher k.
Oh,
that's cool.
Why is that cool? Because we saw how to solve single source shortest paths
in a DAG in linear time. Now, this graph that we're going to construct is
going to have v plus 1 levels.
So could have
our graph
kind of explodes v times.
Right?
We're going to do that in a second. I'm going
to be more precise with what I mean there.
But if
we're multiplying our graph v plus 1 times,
then the size of
our graph is now v times larger.
That's not so hard to believe. But
if we made our graph v times larger
and we ran a shortest path algorithm
in linear time with respect to that graph,
then that graph has
something like size v
times v plus
e size.
That looks familiar maybe?
That's this running time.
Right?
So if we can find an algorithm that runs in
that running time, we can get down to v times e.
OK?
So let's try to do that.
Here's the transformation. I'm going to show
you. I'm going to show you first with an example.
OK?
Here's an example
of a directed graph
that does
contain a negative weight cycle.
OK? Can anyone find it for me?
b,
c,
d. B, c, d. Right? Has weight minus 4 plus
3 minus 1. It has a minus 2
total weight.
Right? So that's
a negative weight cycle.
OK?
So if I were to take shortest paths from a,
right,
I will want to say
at
the end of my algorithm, this better be 0.
And all of these
better be minus infinity.
Right? So that's what
I want in my algorithm.
So what's my algorithm
going to be? I'm going to make v plus 1
copies of this graph.
And I'm going to
kind of stretch it out.
Right? OK. So here I have v,
0, 1, 2, 3, 4. There are four vertices
in my graph. So this is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5
copies of my graph. I have a version of vertex A. For each one of
those copies, a version of vertex B for each of those copies, c and d,
et cetera. OK? So I have this nice grid of
vertices.
And I'm not
going to put any edges
within a layer,
within a level.
Right? Because then, I mean, this graph has
cycles. Right? And I don't want cycles in my graph.
Right? What I'm going to do instead is for every edge
in my original graph, for example, the edge from A to B,
I'm going to connect it
to the B in the next level.
Right? So A0 is connected to B1
with an edge weight of minus 5,
just like in the original.
OK? And I'm going to do that for every edge in
my graph. And I repeat that down all the way.
OK?
In addition, I'm going to add a zero weight edge from A0 to A1, or from
every vertex all the way down the line. These are all zero weight edges
corresponding to, I'm not going to traverse
an edge.
I'm just going
to stay at this vertex.
OK?
That's going to allow us to simulate this at
most k edges condition. Now, if you take a look
at paths
in this graph from A0, our starting vertex,
clearly, none of the other vertices are in that level, are reachable from
A0. Right? Just as we want. Right? Because the shortest path distance
to any
of these vertices using at most zero edges
should be infinite. Right?
I can't get there in zero edges.
OK?
But then any path
in this graph using at most k edges
is going to correspond
to a path from A0
to B3 in this graph.
Would correspond to a
path in this graph that uses at most
three edges. Right? So
let's find such a path.
OK?
So going from A0,
B1,
stay at B1,
stay at B, sorry. Yeah,
that's a path using fewer than three edges,
or at most three edges.
OK? But there's another path here.
Where is it?
Going from A, A, A to B. OK, that's not such
an interesting one. That's the same path.
So I might have more than one path in here
corresponding to a path in there.
But my claim is that any
path in here corresponds to a path in here.
OK?
So what's a path of length?
Three that's non -trivial. Yeah, A to C to
D to B. OK?
So A
to C.
To D
to B.
Yeah, that's a path.
Right? And basically, because I constructed this
so that the edges always move from level to level,
as I traverse these edges,
I always change levels.
Yeah?
But my original graph doesn't have these self loops with
zero A. TANZER. Yes. My original graph doesn't have an edge
from A to A.
That's true.
Right?
So I'm
going to use these edges to correspond to,
I'm deciding not
to take an edge.
Right?
It's not that I'm doing any work here. I'm
just staying there for a state.
OK? And that's what's going to allow me to get this at most edges. All
right. So this is the graph we construct. Hopefully, you understand that we
made these V layers.
Right?
This is V.
And
a vertex, we made V copies of every vertex and
connected them using edges in this way. OK.
So first step of Bellman -Ford is construct
this graph.
So Bellman -Ford, construct
G
prime as described above.
So I have a vertex that has how
many vertices?
V times V plus 1. Right?
V times V plus 1 vertices.
And how many edges?
Well, I
have one edge for outgoing
edge for each vertex corresponding to
just staying in the same place.
Right? So
that's V
squared vertices. I mean, edges.
I have one edge
for every edge in my graph.
I have K. Sorry. I
have V minus 1. Sorry. Just V.
I have V edges for every edge in my graph.
OK? So that means,
so this is the number
of vertices.
And
V times V
plus
V times E.
This is V, V plus E.
All right. Cool.
So that's how many edges I have.
So we construct it in that way. It's a DAG. Right?
If we only have edges going to increasing levels,
then this thing can't have cycles because otherwise, that
would mean there would be an edge pointing backwards.
Right? And
we didn't construct any of those.
All right.
So
we construct this graph G prime.
We can do that in linear time with respect to these things.
I just go through all the edges. I make these edges.
And I make these vertices.
It doesn't take anything. I just
do it naively. Right? I can do that in time
V times V plus E asymptotically.
OK.
Now, I run
DAG relaxation.
Our nice algorithm we
had last time.
From
in there, it was A0. I'm going to say it's
S0, our source.
Our source vertex.
Single source shortest paths.
So that I compute delta
of S0 to VK.
For all K in, what
is it?
0 to V.
Right? That's what
single source shortest paths does.
Right? It computes for me this distance from my source at some source.
Right? To every other vertex in the graph. And so in particular, I get these.
Right?
Well, that is all of them.
So
for each
vertex V,
set
the thing I'm going to return,
d value,
S to V,
equal to
the shortest path distance I got
from DAG relaxation to a particular vertex.
So I'm going to set
this to be V minus 1. All right?
Why am I doing this?
Right? I'm setting it to be the shortest path distance
to the guy in the second to last row here, or column,
in
my modified graph.
The hope is that this distance
in my DAG
corresponds to
this distance
in my original graph. Right?
The distance to V using
at most V minus 1 edges.
Right?
So that's the claim we're going to prove in just a second. I'm
going to write it down just so that we can see it. That we have
just to continue
our train of thought.
Claim
delta S0
VK equals delta K,
the K edge distance
from S to V.
That's what we want to claim.
That would then,
what
would that mean then? That would mean that
I'm correctly setting the shortest
path distance here for all vertices
whose distance is finite.
Great. I mean, I set
values to things where they're not
finite, where they're minus infinity also.
But in particular,
I set the ones correctly if they're finite.
OK. So the last thing we need to do
is deal with these minus infinity vertices.
Right?
But we know
how to do that. Right?
We just look at the witnesses.
Because we've computed this value
for
K equals V and K equals V minus 1.
And if that claim over there is true,
then those shortest path distances are the
same as these K edge shortest path distances.
And we can just,
for every vertex, we compare these things.
If this is satisfied, we got a witness.
Right? OK.
So for each witness
u in V,
where delta
S0 u V,
is less than
strictly S0 u V minus 1,
that's the definition
of a witness here.
Close the parentheses.
Then for each vertex V reachable
from u,
set delta, sorry, d.
Returning
d of S V equal to minus infinity.
So that's the
end of the algorithm.
Basically, I'm looking
for all the witnesses.
For each witness, I find all the vertices reachable from
it and set it to minus infinity, just as we argued before.
OK. So
it remains to prove this claim.
How do we prove this claim?
Well,
we can induct on K. Right?
Is this true for K equals 0?
Yeah. Right? We kind of already argued it over here when we were
talking about our initialization step or what DAG relaxation does.
It'll set this to be the shortest path from
this guy to all these vertices.
These aren't reachable
from here. And so these are infinite.
And that one's 0.
OK.
So the base case,
so
induct
on K.
Base case,
K equals 0. Check.
Right?
That's all good.
Now we induct
in our inductive step.
Let's take a look at the shortest path distance
from S0 to V of K prime for some K prime.
And the assumption is, the inductive hypothesis is, that this distance is
the K edge distance for all K prime less than K. I mean, all K less than K
prime.
Right?
Well, kind of
by definition of a shortest path,
this is the minimum over
all incoming vertices of the shortest path
from S0 to U of
K prime minus 0.
Minus 1 plus
the weight of the edge
from U of K prime minus 1
to VK
prime
for all U K prime minus
1 in the adjacencies,
the incoming
adjacencies of VK prime.
OK. What does this mean?
Right?
I'm just saying,
graph G prime,
a shortest path to this vertex needs to go first through
some vertex in the layer before it, which is one of these.
And
in particular, I'm only connected to things
adjacent to me.
That's all this is saying. I have to go through that vertex
and take some shortest path to one of those previous vertices.
Now, in actuality,
these adjacencies, I constructed them to be
similar to the adjacencies in my original graph
in addition to one edge coming from
my original vertex, from vertex v.
So this is the same as
the minimum
of this set delta S0.
Same thing.
Plus w u v for all
u in the incoming adjacencies
of my original vertex
in addition
to one more term. What is that other term?
These
are all of the things corresponding to my incoming edges in my original
thing. But I also have that one edge coming from the v before it. So this is,
I'm going to
union this with delta S0
v of k prime minus 1.
Awful.
I think there's another
one here.
This is S0 v of k prime minus 1.
I'm not going to rewrite it.
OK.
Then by induction,
this thing and this
thing must be the edge shortest paths using
k minus 1 vertices.
And then
that's just the statement
of what the shortest path should
be using at most k
prime edges going from S to v.
OK.
So
these things are
the same as we claimed.
Yay. Check.
All right. And then it's not such a trivial, it's kind of a
trivial leap then to say that at the end of Bellman -Ford,
these guys,
sorry, the
things that we return,
these guys
are the shortest path distances.
Because here, if they're finite,
we set them to their true shortest path
distance. And if they're minus infinity,
that invariant means that these things
correspond to exactly this claim over here.
It's a witness.
And then finding all the vertices reachable
from those witnesses,
we set all of the infinite ones
to be minus infinity as desired.
OK. So what's the running time of
this thing?
Well, we had to construct this graph. So we
had to take that time.
OK.
We ran dag relaxation. That takes the same
amount of time.
Right. For
every vertex, we did order v work.
And then for each witness,
how many could there be? Most v.
Checking
the reachability of each vertex,
that can be done in how long?
Order e time.
Right.
Because we don't need to consider the things that aren't
connected to x or aren't connected to the witness.
Right. So this thing takes order
v times e work.
So we're upper bounded by this time it took
to construct the original graph.
And then
we're going to buy the claim we had before.
That takes v times e time. OK.
So that's Bellman -Ford.
I'm just going to leave
you with two nuggets.
First,
the shortest path,
if for any witness, let's say we have a
witness here. Do I have any witnesses here?
But
is there a vertex
on this cycle that goes through,
who has the shortest path,
that goes through four vertices
that's smaller than any other? Right.
OK. I can go from a to c to b
to d to b to c.
And you can work out this algorithm. I have
it in the notes that you can take a look at.
This
will actually have a shorter path
for vertex. Sorry. It'll
have a shorter path for vertex b.
a to b to c to d to b. Thank you.
That's a path of length four of four edges.
That has shorter path than any path that has fewer edges. In
particular, there's only one other path to b. Using fewer than four.
There's two other paths.
One path of length that has one edge that has
weight minus five. And one path, this path,
that has weight nine minus one is
eight.
Right.
Whereas this path, minus five, minus four,
three, minus one, has
minus 10 plus three is minus seven,
which is shorter than minus five.
So b indeed is a witness.
Right.
And if we actually take a look at that path
through this graph,
going from a to b
to c to d
back to b,
we see that there's
a negative weight cycle in this graph. b to c to d to
b. And indeed, that's always the case for our witnesses.
OK. You can see a proof
of that in the notes.
And you can see in recitation a little
space optimization to
make us not have
to construct this entire graph on the fly,
but actually only use order v space while
we're going. OK. So that's Bellman -Ford.
Sorry for running a little late.